<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A daily exercise for ladies and gentlewomen Whereby they may learne and practice the whole art of making pastes, preserues, marmalades, conserues, tartstuffes, gellies, breads, sucket candies, cordiall vvaters, conceits in sugar-vvorkes of seuerall kindes. As also to dry lemonds, orenges, or other fruits. Newly set forth, according to the now approued receipts, vsed both by honourable and vvorshipfull personages. By Iohn Murrell, professour thereof.</title>
            <author>Murrell, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101449</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837263</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837263</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1578</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1578)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 997:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A daily exercise for ladies and gentlewomen Whereby they may learne and practice the whole art of making pastes, preserues, marmalades, conserues, tartstuffes, gellies, breads, sucket candies, cordiall vvaters, conceits in sugar-vvorkes of seuerall kindes. As also to dry lemonds, orenges, or other fruits. Newly set forth, according to the now approued receipts, vsed both by honourable and vvorshipfull personages. By Iohn Murrell, professour thereof.</title>
                  <author>Murrell, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Snodham] for the vvidow Helme, and are to be sould at her shop in S. Dunstans church-yard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹²  (-A1 and 12, blank?) B-G¹²  (-G11-12, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: some pages stained and mutilated with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cookery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Canning and preserving --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Daily</hi> EXERCISE for LADIES and GENTLEWOMEN.</p>
            <p>Whereby they may learne and practiſe the whole Art of making Paſtes, Preſerues, Marma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lades, Conſerues, Tartſtuffes, Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Breads, Sucket Candies, Cordiall vvaters, Conceits in Sugar-vvorkes of ſeuerall kindes.</p>
            <p>As alſo to dry <hi>Lemonds, Orenges,</hi> or other Fruits.</p>
            <p>Newly ſet forth, according to the new approued Receipts, vſed both by Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Worſhipfull perſonages.</p>
            <p>BY IOHN MVRREL Profeſſor thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the vvidovv <hi>Helme,</hi> and are to be ſould at her ſhop in <hi>S. Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO MY MVCH HONOVRED THE TRVLY VERTVOVS, M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> ELIZABETH BINGHAM, wife of <hi>Nicholas Bingham</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen; ſo, nothing old (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the <hi>Olde of dayes</hi>) can pleaſe <hi>Soule,</hi> or <hi>Senſe:</hi> Yet
<pb facs="tcp:1578:3"/>on olde <hi>Grounds</hi> are new <hi>Deſcants</hi> daily, as full of <hi>rarietie,</hi> as <hi>varietie:</hi> that doth pleaſe; the pleaſure of <hi>Man</hi> conſiſting in nothing more, than in euery thing; that is, in change: <hi>varietie</hi> ſtanding more aloofe from <hi>ſacietie,</hi> than <hi>vniformitie,</hi> in whatſoeuer ſenſible.</p>
            <p>Wee alter our <hi>Faſhions</hi> and outward <hi>Habits</hi> daily; the <hi>whiteſt Ruffe</hi> being not long ſince thought the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt wearing; then the <hi>blew;</hi> and now the <hi>yealow:</hi> So, our <hi>Cookery, Paſtry, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillations,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:3"/>Conſerues,</hi> and <hi>Preſerues,</hi> are farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe now, than not long ſince they were; Daily <hi>Practiſe</hi> and <hi>Obſeruation</hi> finding out eyther what to adde or detract from olde <hi>Formes</hi> in eyther of theſe kindes; or to make new much more pleaſing and profitable. Theſe are all, (or, at leaſt, the moſt) of the neweſt Straine; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued and beloued of thoſe that try them. What elſe they are I referre to your iudgement, and my
<pb facs="tcp:1578:4"/>ſelfe to your good fauour; euer remaining,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The humble louer of your manifold vertues,</hi> IO: MVRREL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:4"/>
            <head>The generall Table of this Booke: Whereof the firſt containeth Paſtes, Preſerues, Marmalades, Conſerues, Tartſtuffes, Gellies, &amp;c.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Paſtes.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O make Paſte of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia,</hi> againſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Paſte of <hi>Genua. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Paſte of <hi>Pomcittron. 3</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:5"/>
            <list>
               <head>Marmalades.</head>
               <item>TO make Marmalade of Quinces. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Marmalade red of Quinces, commonly called Lump-Marmalade, that ſhall looke as red as a Rubie. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Marmalade of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make greene Marmalade of Pippins. <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make red Marmalade that ſhall looke very orient. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make <hi>Dia Setonia</hi> of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:5"/>
            <list>
               <head>Conſerues.</head>
               <item>TO make Conſerue of Violets. <hi>32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Conſerue of Barberries. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Conſerue of Roſes. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Conſerue of <hi>Gelliflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make conſerue of Cowſlips. <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Conſerue of Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golds. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Conſerue of Damſons. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Tartſtuffes.</head>
               <item>TO make Tart-ſtuffe of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to keep all the yeer. <hi>39</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:6"/>
               <item>To make tartſtuffe of Prunes. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make white tartſtuffe. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make yealow tartſtuffe. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Gellies.</head>
               <item>TO make Quiddeniock. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Chryſtall Gellie. <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To preſerue Pippins to lie in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gellie. <hi>45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Gellie of Pippins, of Amber colour. <hi>46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Gellie of Pippins as ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent red as any Rubie. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Leach of Almonds of diuers pleaſing colours. <hi>48</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:6"/>
            <list>
               <head>Breads.</head>
               <item>TO make red Ginger-bread otherwiſe called. Leach Lumbar. <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make white Ginger-bread. <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Italian Bisket. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make <hi>Ginetoes. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Prince Bisket. <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make French <hi>Macaroones. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Naples Bisket. <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Shelbread. <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Counteſſe Cakes. <hi>57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make a fine Sugar Cake. <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>Rough Rock Candies.</head>
               <item>TO make rocke <hi>de Cittron. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To rough rock Candie Orenges dried with Sugar. <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To rough Candie ſprigs, or bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Roſemarie. <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To rough Candie all flowers. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Sucket Candies.</head>
               <item>TO ſucket Candie greene Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds: <hi>63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſucket Candie greene Ginger. <hi>64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſucket Candie Walnuts. <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſucket Candie Peaches, or any greene Plumme before it be ſtoned. <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>Cordiall Waters.</head>
               <item>TO make <hi>Aqua Coeleſtis. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Cinamon Water. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Steuens</hi> water. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Balme water. <hi>70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Angelica water. <hi>71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Wormwood water. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Conceits in Sugar-works.</head>
               <item>TO make March-pane Paſte. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make a March-pane. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make any conceit in March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane ſtuffe. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make any other ſmall conceits in Sugar worke or Almond
<pb facs="tcp:1578:8"/>paſte, or Sugar plate paeſte. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Snailes, Snakes, &amp;c. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Shoes, Slippers, &amp;c. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make letters or knots, &amp;c. <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Walnuts both ſhell and kernell. <hi>80</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Sugar-Workes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort.</head>
               <item>TO make Sugar plate paſte. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Paſte of ſundry flowers. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Pennet. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Cinamon ſticks by Art. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Calliſhones. <hi>85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Muſcachones. <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Muſcadinaes. <hi>87</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Table.</head>
               <item>To make Troſes for the cold. <hi>88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Cinamon Letters. <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Canalones in ſpices. <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Ruskilians. <hi>91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Gentilliſſoes. <hi>92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Nouelliſſoes. <hi>93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Lozenges of Violets. <hi>94</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>To drie Fruits.</head>
               <item>TO drie Orenges or Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds. <hi>95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To dry white Peare-Plums. <hi>96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To dry black Peare-Plums. <hi>97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To dry Pippins as cleere as Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To dry Apricockes orient and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie cleere. <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To dry Peares without any Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. <hi>100</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:9"/>
            <list>
               <head>Phyſicall Receipts.</head>
               <item>TO make ſirupe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolets. <hi>101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make ſirupe of Liquorice. <hi>102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make ſirupe of Roſes ſolutiue. <hi>103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make ſirupe of drie Roſes. <hi>104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt the trembling of the heart. <hi>105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt the riſing of the mother <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An almond milke. <hi>107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt looſeneſſe of the Bodie. <hi>108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Receipt for a vomit. <hi>109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt extreame coughing. <hi>110</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:9"/>
               <item>Order of Colours. <hi>111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colours edible, <hi>112</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To colour Leach. <hi>113</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="advert">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:10"/>
            <p>GEntle Reader, if any ſhall bee deſirous to buy any of the moulds wherein any of the formes ſpecified in the Booke fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are made, they may haue them alſo where theſe Bookes are to be ſould.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:11"/>
            <head>Of Paſtes.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Paſte of <hi>Regia</hi> againſt a Conſumption.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake two Quailes, two Roales, two Partridges, a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of cock Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, the brawne of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, roaſt theſe readie to be eaten; take the fleſh from the bone, and beate it fine in an Alabaſter mortar, with two ounces of the pith of Veale growing in the backe, a quarter of a pound of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaceas,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1578:12"/>halfe a drachme of Amber-greece, a graine of Musk, halfe a pound of white Sugar-candie beaten fine: put all theſe into an Alabaſter morter, beat it to a perfect Paſte, now and then putting in a ſpoonefull of Goates milke, put in two or three graines of Bezar, when you haue beaten all to a perfect Paſte, make it vp in little round cakes, and ſo bake it vp on a ſheete of paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Paſte of <hi>Genua,</hi> as they doe beyond the Seas.</head>
               <p n="2">2 BOile faire yellow Peare-Quinces tender in their
<pb facs="tcp:1578:12"/>skinnes, and ſo let them ſtand vntill the next day, till they be colde, then pare them, and ſcrape all the pulp from the coare, then take as much pulp of yellow Peaches as the pulp of Quinces doth weigh, and dry it vpon a little chafingdiſh of coales, alwaies ſtirring it, then boile the weight of both theſe pulps in double refined Sugar, and ſo let it boile, alway ſtirring it vntill it come to a candie height, with as much Roſe-water as will melt that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and put in your pulps, alway ſtirring it in the boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, vntill it come from the the bottome of the Poſnet,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:13"/>then faſhion it vpon a pie plate, or a ſheete of glaſſe, ſome like leaues, ſome like halfe fruits, and ſome you may print with moulds, ſet them into a warme Ouen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the breadis drawne, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Stoue, the next day you may turne them, and when the ſtuffe is through dry, you may box it, and keepe it for all the yeere, but be ſure it be through dried before you lay it vp in ſtore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:13"/>
               <head>To make Marble Paſte of Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cittron, an excellent Cordiall paſte.</head>
               <p n="3">3 TAke the yelloweſt Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cittrons that you can get, pare them, and cut them in quarters, and take out the meate, and as ſoone as you haue cut and pared a piece, throw it into a baſon of colde water, then ſet on a Pipkin of faire water, and ſo ſoone as it boyleth, take out your pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and drie them in a faire cloath, and put them into the ſeething liquor, and let them boile vntill they be tender, but ſhift them three or foure times
<pb facs="tcp:1578:14"/>in the boyling to take away the bitterneſſe, powre them into a Colender, and drie them againe in a faire cloath, and ſtampe them in a ſtone morter, then boile the weight of the pulp in double refined Sugar vnto a Candie height, and put the pulp into the boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sugar, and ſo let it boile leaſurely, alway ſtirring it, and when it growes ſtiffe, powre it on a plate or ſheete of glaſſe reaſonable thinne in a broad cake, and ſtoue it, the next day cut it in lozenges, and turne them vpon a ſheete of white paper, then waſh your glaſſe or plate, and lay them on againe vntill they be
<pb facs="tcp:1578:14"/>through dry, box them and keepe them all the yeere. If you pleaſe wrap a graine of Muske in a paper, and let it lie in the bottome of the box, it will adde to the pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Marble Paſte, called the Italian Chippe.</head>
               <p n="4">4 TAke Violets, Cowſlips, and Cloue-gilliflowers, dry them and beate them to fine powder, mingle them with double refined Sugar, cearſed through a tiffanie or a lawne Sieue, make it vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sugar plate, with a little gum dragon ſteept in Roſe water and milke, when you
<pb facs="tcp:1578:15"/>haue made your plate, then rowle euery piece thinne and lay each vpon other, and ſo rowle them vp in round rowles, as you would rowle vp a leafe of paper, then cut it end waies, and rowle it as thinne as a paper, and ſo it will looke finely ſheckled like a piece of Marble. In like manner you may make Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlane diſhes or trenchers of that ſtuffe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Paſte of Apricockes or Peare plums.</head>
               <p n="5">5 TAke the faireſt of theſe fruits that you can get, and take out the ſtones, then
<pb facs="tcp:1578:15"/>boile them ſoftly betwixt two diſhes without any liquor, and when they be ſoft, drie them ſomewhat drie, then take them off the fire, and put them vpon a ſheete of white paper, then boile the weight of the pulp in double refined Sugar vnto a Candie height, with as much Roſe-water as will melt it, and put your pulp into the hot Sugar, and if you pleaſe: put a graine of Muske into the boiling, and ſo let it boile vntill it be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtiffe, then faſhion it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſheete of glaſſe in what forme you thinke fit, and ſo let it drie in a Stoue or warme Ouen, the next day turne it
<pb facs="tcp:1578:16"/>and put it into the Ouen or Stoue againe, and when it is through dry, it will looke as cleare as Amber: ſo you may vſe all kinde of Plums.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Paſte of Pippins, after the <hi>Genua</hi> faſhion, ſome like leaues, ſome like Plums, with ſtalkes and ſtones.</head>
               <p n="6">6 TAke and pare faire yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Pippins, cut them in ſmall pieces, ſtew them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two diſhes with two or three ſpoonefuls of Roſe-water, and when they be boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led very tender, ſtraine them, then boile the weight of the
<pb facs="tcp:1578:16"/>pulp in double refined Sugar vnto a Candie height, and if you pleaſe put in a graine of Muske, and a quarter of an ounce of fine white Ginger ſearced, and ſo let it boile vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you ſee it come from the bottome of the Poſnet, then faſhion it on a ſheete of glaſſe in ſome prettie forme as you thinke beſt, and ſtoue it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Stoue, or in a warme Ouen. If you deſire to haue any of it red, colour it with a ſpoonefull of Conſerue of Damſons, before you faſhion it vpon your glaſſe or plate, and that will make it ſhew as though it were made of red Plums. If you put a ſtone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb facs="tcp:1578:17"/>two halfes, will ſhew like a Plum, you may keepe Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſtalkes drie for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Paſte of <hi>Eringus</hi> rontes.</head>
               <p n="7">7 TAke halfe a pound of <hi>Eringus</hi> roots newly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, the youngeſt that you can get, cut them in ſhort pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like dice, then ſtampe them in a mortar fine, blanch and beate into fine Paſte a quarter of a pound of <hi>Iordane</hi> Almonds, take three ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Damaske Roſe-water, one ſpoonefull of <hi>Aqua Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestis,</hi> a graine of Muske, two
<pb facs="tcp:1578:17"/>graines of Amber-greece, a graine of Bezar ſtone, then take halfe a pound of <hi>Piſtaceus</hi> (which being crackt and pild, will not be aboue an ounce &amp; a halfe) when you haue taken off the husks, beat them fine, and put them to your Paſte, beat all together in a faire A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labaſter morter then beat the weight of your pulp in fine Sugar-candy, &amp; put it to the pulp, &amp; ſo beat it againe, then take it out and ſet it on a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingdiſh of coales, and dry it, alwaies ſtirring it vntill you ſee it turn ſomwhat white and dry, then lay it in little lumps vpon white paper, &amp; ſo dry in a Stoue, &amp; keep it all the yeere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:18"/>
               <head>To make an excellent greene Paſte without any colouring.</head>
               <p n="8">8 QVoddle greene Apples reaſonably tender, pill off the outward skinne, and throw all the barke of the Apples into a Poſnet of ſeeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water, and ſo let it boile as faſt as it can vntill it turne greene, then take them vp and ſtraine the pulp, then boile the weight of it in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar to a Candie height, and put your pulp into the ſeeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sugar, and let it boile vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it grow ſtiffe, then faſhion it on a pie-plate, or a ſheete of
<pb facs="tcp:1578:18"/>glaſſe, and pint it on mowlds, and drie it in a Stoue or a warme Ouen ſome tenne or twelue dayes, that it be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly drie, and then you may keepe it all the yeere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Almond Paſte.</head>
               <p n="9">9 BLanch and beate <hi>Iordane</hi> Almonds in a ſtone mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, put in now and then a ſpoonefull of Roſe-water to keepe it from oyling, and when they be very fine, put about a pound and a halfe of fine Sugar to two pound of Almonds, halfe a drachme of Muske, and as much Roſe-water as will ſerue to beat it
<pb facs="tcp:1578:19"/>to a perfect Paſte, which you may eaſily gueſſe by your owne diſcretion beginning with one ſpoonefull, and ſo adding as you ſhall ſee fit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Paſte of <hi>Enula-cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana</hi> rootes an excellent cordiall Paſte, and good againſt the cough of the lungs.</head>
               <p n="10">10 LAy the youngeſt of theſe rootes in water, and then boile them tender, ſhift them three or foure times to take away their bitterneſſe, pill them, pith them, and beat them in a morter, with the weight of eighteene pence of
<pb facs="tcp:1578:19"/>theſe ſeuerall ſirups, <hi>videlicet,</hi> Maydenhaire, Iſope, and Horehound: when you haue beaten all this fine, draw them through a ſtrainer, with the pap of two roſted Pippins, and a graine of Muske, then dry it a little on a chafingdiſh of coales, vntill you ſee it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be ſomewhat ſtiffe, then boile the weight thereof in double refined Sugar vnto a Candie height, and put the pulp into the Sugar, let it boile with continuall ſtirring, vntill it be ſomewhat ſtiffe, then drop it on a plate or ſheete of glaſſe, dry it and keepe it in a Stoue.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:20"/>
            <head>Preſerues.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Peare-plums greene.</head>
               <p n="11">11 BOile a pound and a halfe of Sugar, with as much wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as will melt it, with a pound of the beſt Peare-plummes that you can get, your Plums muſt firſt be waſht and dried in a faire cloath; let them boile ſoftly the ſpace of an houre, and then take them vp, and put them into a ſiluer or an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then diſh, when they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb facs="tcp:1578:20"/>colde, put them into the Sugar againe, and let them boile vntill they be tender, and the corner of the ſtone ſweet, then take them vp, and coole them againe as before, vntill they be almoſt colde, and whilſt they be a cooling boile your ſirupe ſomething thick, and betweene hot and colde, put them vp and keepe them, they will be greene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue other Plums greene.</head>
               <p n="12">12 TAke your Plums while they be hard vpon the trees, ſcald them in faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and take them vp, and
<pb facs="tcp:1578:21"/>couer them in a preſeruing pan with Sugar, and boile them tender, and then take them vp, and boile the ſirup by it ſelfe vntill it be ſomwhat thick, then betweene hot and colde pot them vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Cherries.</head>
               <p n="13">13 TAke the weight of your Cherries in Sugar, and with a ſiluer ſpoone bruiſe as many other-Cherries in a poſnet, boile them vntill the ſirup be ſomewhat red, then ſtraine that liquor through a cuſhion canuas into another faire poſnet, then diuide your Sugar into three parts, and
<pb facs="tcp:1578:21"/>put one part into the red ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup, &amp; ſo ſoone as the Sugar is melted take it off the fire, &amp; ſcum it cleane, then cut the ſtalkes off the Cherries ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhort, and croſſe them one by one with a ſharp knife on the end, then put the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries into the red liquor, and make them boile as faſt as they can, vntill they riſe vp frothie, then take them off the fire and ſcum them, and then put in the ſecond part of the Sugar into them, &amp; ſet them on the fire againe &amp; let them boile as faſt as they can, and when they boile vp, take it off and ſcum it, then put in the third part of Sugar, &amp; yet
<pb facs="tcp:1578:22"/>againe ſet it ouer the fire, and when it riſeth vp frothie, take it off and ſcum it very cleane, then ſet them on the fire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be ſomething thick, you may know when they are enough by dropping a little on a ſawcer on the bottome of it, if it be thicke like gellie; then take them off the fire, and powre them into an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then platter, and being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene hot and colde, put them vp in a gally pot, or put them in gallie-pots to keepe all the yeere, but put a piece of white paper on them, and couer them with a piece of parchment or ſoft leather.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:22"/>
               <head>To preſerue Quinces red.</head>
               <p n="14">14 PAre and core yellow Peare-quinces, parboile them in faire water, then cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your Sugar, and take to euery pound of Sugar an Ale-pint of water, and when your Sugar is clarified, ſtraine it into a preſeruing pan, and put your Quinces into that hot Sugar, and ſo let them boile cloſe couered, now and then ſtirring them, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them to keepe them from breaking, and when you ſee your Quinces tender, and looke very red, take them vp, and boile the ſirupe by it
<pb facs="tcp:1578:23"/>ſelfe, vntill you ſee it ſome what thicke, then betweene hot and colde, pot them or put them in glaſſes as was ſaid in Cherries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Wardens.</head>
               <p n="15">15 PArboile your Wardens reaſonable tender in faire water, let them ſtand vntill they be colde, then pare them and pricke them with a knife two or three pricks in euery Warden, and ſo couer them in clarified Sugar, with a piece of whole Cinamon, a ſlice or two of pared Ginger, and three Cloues, boile them leaſurely cloſe couered, vntill
<pb facs="tcp:1578:23"/>they be red and tender, then boile the ſirupe by it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Pippins greene.</head>
               <p n="16">16 GAther greene Pippins eſpecially from the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-boughes, and in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; quoddle them in two ſeuerall waters, and to euery one of theſe Pippins take a pound of Sugar, clarifie it well and very cleare, and put in your Pippins, and let them boile leaſurely, and they will turne greene as any Leeke. Take them now and then off the fire, and turne them with a ſpoone, and ſet them ouer the fire againe three or foure
<pb facs="tcp:1578:24"/>times, alwaies turning them, and warming them, and when your Pippins bevery tender: take them vp, and boile the ſirupe a little by it ſelfe, then betwixt hot and colde pot them. If you pleaſe you may put in a graine of Muske, and a few Cloues, it will much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Pippins of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Amber.</head>
               <p n="17">17 PAre and bore a hole through a pound of Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins as ſmall as a wheat ſtraw, couer them with Sugar in a preſeruing pan (the Sugar being firſt clarified) with a
<pb facs="tcp:1578:24"/>graine of Muske, and a piece of Cinamon, ſo let them boile leaſurely, vncouered, when they be tender, take them out and boile the ſirupe a little by it ſelfe, then pot the Pippins blood warme, &amp; keepe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Barberries red.</head>
               <p n="18">18 TAke out the ſtones from the faireſt Barberries, that you can get, and take foure times their weight in Sugar, then take as much iuice of other Barberries, as wil diſſolue the one part, then put it into a skillet, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue this part of Sugar vpon the fire, then put in your Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:25"/>and let them boile up, then beat the ſecond part of your Sugar, and put it in, and make it boile up againe, and put in the reſt, and couer it cloſe, and let it boile untill they be enough, then take them up and ſcum them, and ſo let them ſtand, and between hot and colde not them up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Barberries white.</head>
               <p n="19">19 STone the faireſt Barberries that you can get, take foure times their weight in sugar, then take as much faire water as will diſſolue one part, and put it in a skillet on the fire, and when it is
<pb facs="tcp:1578:25"/>diſſolued put in your Barber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and let them boile vp, then put in the other of your parts, beat it firſt and put it in, then let them ſtand, and boile vp againe alwaies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and put in the reſt, boile it, and ſcum it againe, coole it and pot it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Pippins red.</head>
               <p n="20">20 BOre a hole of the bigneſſe of a wheat ſtraw quite through a pound of Pippins, couer them with Sugar in a preſeruing pan, put in a piece of Muske, a piece of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and ſo let them boile cloſe couered very leaſurely
<pb facs="tcp:1578:26"/>vntill they be tender, then boile the ſirupe by it ſelfe, coole it and pot it, and the Pippins blood-warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue white Peare-plums.</head>
               <p n="21">21 TAke a pound of the beſt Peare-plums that you get, and with their weight in Sugar, ſet them on the fire with halfe a pint of faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vntill it be diſſolued, then take it off, let it coole vntill it be but blood-warme, put in your Plums, and let them ſtand about a quarter of an houre vpon a ſoft fire, and let them ſtand vntill their
<pb facs="tcp:1578:26"/>skinnes be broken, then take them off and ſcum them, and let them ſtand vntill they be colde, then ſet them on the fire againe, and boile them a pace vntill they be ſoft, then take them off againe, and ſcum them, coole them, and pot them: if your ſirupe be too thinne, boile it a little by it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Orenges or Lemonds rindes.</head>
               <p n="22">22 DRiue off the vttermoſt skinne of your Orenges with a raſp, cut them in two, and take out the core quite and cleane, and let the pils
<pb facs="tcp:1578:27"/>lie in water three or foure daies, then boile them tender in ſixe or ſeauen waters, leaſt their bitterneſſe be diſtaſtfull, then take them vp, and drie them in a very faire cloath, and put them to as much Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar clarified as will couer them: let them boile ſoftly ouer the fire halfe an houre at leaſt, and reſt in that ſirupe three or foure daies, after that time heat them throughly, and take them out of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe, and ſtrengthen it with freſh Sugar boiled therein halfe an houre, coole it, and being blood-warme, pot vp your fruit in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:27"/>
               <head>To preſerue greene Peaches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be ſtoned.</head>
               <p n="23">23 SCald your Peaches, being ſo young that you may thruſt a pinne through them, rub off the furre with a piece of courſe linnen cloath, then pricke them with a ſharpe knife, and boile them tender in as much clarified Sugar as will couer them, then take them vp and boile the ſirupe by it ſelfe, vntill it be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thick, and being blood-warme with cooling, put in your fruit and pot it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:28"/>
               <head>To preſerue greene Walnuts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be ſhelled.</head>
               <p n="24">24 TAke your Walnuts alſo when they may eaſily be pierced with a pin, pare them thinne, and lay them a weeke together in brine, then par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boile them very tender in ſeauen or eight waters, then take them vp, and dry them with a faire cloath, and ſticke in euery one two or three Cloues, and couer them in clarified Sugar, and boile them a good houre cloſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, then powre them into an earthen pot, and let them ſtand a weeke, &amp; then warme
<pb facs="tcp:1578:28"/>them againe, and powre them into a Colender, to let the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe drop from them; then boile the ſirupe by itſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be ſomewhat thicke with freſh Sugar, and being but warme pot them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Damſons.</head>
               <p n="25">25 TAke two pounds of the faireſt Damſons, and one pound of hard Sugar, halfe a pinte of faire water, ſet it on the fire vntill it be diſſolued in a preſeruing pan, lay your Damſons in milke-warme water, and put them into the diſſolued Sugar, make a ſoft fire, and when it beginneth
<pb facs="tcp:1578:29"/>to boyle: ſcum it continually an houre long, but let it boile ſoftly vncouered, for breaking the Damſons, then take them out, and lay them in an earthen or ſiluer diſh, and let your ſirupe boile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and when they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt colde, put them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and let them boile ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vntill the kernell be both ſweet and tender, cracke the ſtone, and trie, then take your Damſons vp, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt hot and colde pot them, and put them in glaſſes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:29"/>
            <head>Marmulades.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Marmulade of Quinces.</head>
               <p n="26">26 PArboyle yellowe Peare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinces tender in their skins, and let them ſtand in a Tray all night, vntill they be colde, then pare them as thin as you can, for the beſt of the Quince groweth next the skin, then ſcrape all the pulp from the core, for it is grauelly, and therefore goe not too neere: then beat the weight of the pulp in double refined Sugar, with one grain
<pb facs="tcp:1578:30"/>of Muske, and three graines of Amber-greece, &amp; as much Damaske Roſe-water as will diſſolue the Sugar, boile it to a Candie height, then put in your pulp, alwaies ſtirring it ſtill till it come from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Poſnet, box it, and keepe it till occaſion call for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make rough red Marmalade of Quinces, commonly called lump-Marmalade, that ſhall laoke as red as any Rubie.</head>
               <p n="27">27 PAre ripe and well colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Peare-quinces, and cut them in pieces like dice,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:30"/>parboile them very tender, or rather reaſonably tender in faire water, then powre them into a Colender, and let the water runne from them into a cleane Baſon, then ſtraine that water through a ſtrainer into a Poſnet, for if there be any grauell in the Quinces, it will be in that water: Then take the weight of the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in double refined Sugar very fine, put halfe thereof into the Poſnet, into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with it a graine of Muske, a ſlice or two of Ginger tied in a thrid, and let it boile co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered cloſe, vntill you ſee your Sugar come to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Claret wine, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer
<pb facs="tcp:1578:31"/>it, and take out your Ginger, and ſo let it boile vntill your ſirupe begin to conſume away, then take it off the fire, and pomice it with a ladle, and ſo ſtirre it and coole it, and it will looke thick like tart-ſtuffe, then put in your other halfe of your Sugar, and ſo let it boile, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſtirring it vntill it come from the bottome of the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, then box it, and it will looke red like a Rubie, the putting of the laſt Sugar brings it to an orient colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:31"/>
               <head>To make Marmulade of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens a moſt cordiall Marmulade.</head>
               <p n="28">28 BAke the beſt Wardens that you can get in an Ouen with wheaten bread, or longer time then that, let them ſtand in an Ouen in an earthen Panne, but beware they be not burnt, then cut them in ſmall pieces like Dice from the core, and beate them in a ſtone mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then take the weight of the pulp in fine Sugar, and boile it to a Candie height, and put the pulp into the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar boiling hot, with a little
<pb facs="tcp:1578:32"/>beaten and cearſed Ginger, and a graine of Muske, and ſo let it boile, alway ſtirring it vntill it come from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Poſnet, box it, dry it and vſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Marmulade of Pippins.</head>
               <p n="29">29 PAre greene Pippins, cut them in pieces, and boile them tender betwixt two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, when they be tender ſtraine them, then melt the weight of the pulp in Sugar with Roſe-water, and boile it to a Candie height; put in two or three ſpoonefuls of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon water, a thimble full of
<pb facs="tcp:1578:32"/>beaten Cinamon, two thim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles full of Fennell ſeede bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten together, throw all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the boiling Sugar, &amp;c. as in the laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make red Marmulade of Pippins, orient and cleare.</head>
               <p n="30">30 TAke the quantitie of a pound of the afore-ſaid pulp, and put to it two ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Conſerue of Bullice, and ſo ſtirre it together, and your pulp will looke as red as a Cherrie, boile the weight thereof in Sugar vnto a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die height, with two or three ſpoonfuls of Cinamon water,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:33"/>then put in the red pulp into the hot Sugar, and doe as in other Marmulades.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make <hi>Dia Setonia</hi> of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, a cordiall for the ſtomack.</head>
               <p n="31">31 TAke the iuice of good, large, and ripe Quinces, being well waſht, and cleane wipt with a faire cloath, take out the core, and cut the reſt in ſmall pieces, and ſtamp them like crabs, &amp; ſtrain them euen as vergis, to euery pinte of that liquour take halfe a pound of white Sugar-candie, and a graine of Muske, boile it as thicke as Quiddeniock, pot it, and vſe it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:33"/>
            <head>Conſerues.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Conſerue of Violets.</head>
               <p n="32">32 PIcke cleane the blewe ſingle gard in Violets, ſtamp halfe a pound of them fine in an Alabaſter morter, very fine, put two or three ounces of Sugar-candie to the beating of them, and ſo ſoone as your Sugar comes vnto it, it will haue a very pleaſant colour, then lay it on a white paper, and boyle the weight of it in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar vnto a Candie height,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:34"/>and put in the pulp, and let it boile a walme or two, and coole it with a ſiluer ſpoone, and being almoſt colde, pot it and vſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Conſerue of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries.</head>
               <p n="33">33 IN the heat of the day ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the faireſt red Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, pick them cleane, and put them into a deepe pot, and ſet in boiling water vntill they be tender, then ſtraine them through a cuſhion canuas. and boile thrice their weight in double refined Sugar to a Candie height, and coole it a little, and put in your pulp,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:34"/>and boile it halfe an houre, coole it againe vntill it be blood-warme, and then pot it vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Conſerue of Roſes in the beſt manner.</head>
               <p n="34">34 CVt off the white of red Roſe-buds, ſtamp them very fine in a ſtone morter, beat their weight in fine Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, &amp; put it to your flowers, and beat them together in a ſtone morter a whole houre together at the leaſt, vntill they be very fine, then boile it in like quantity of Sugar vnto a Candie height, and put your pulp into the boiling
<pb facs="tcp:1578:35"/>Sugar, when it hath boiled a while, coole it againe with your ſpatter, and wring in the iuyce of a Lemond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Conſerue of Gilliflowers.</head>
               <p n="35">35 GAther red Cloue-Gilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowers in the heat of the day, clip them very ſhort, one leafe into eight or nine pieces at the leaſt, for the ſhorter you clip them, the ſooner they will be beaten fine: then beat them with the quantity of halfe their weight in double refined Sugar, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the pulp be inough, which you may eaſily know both
<pb facs="tcp:1578:35"/>by taſte and feeling, then boile the ſame quantitie of the ſame Sugar to a Candie height, with as much Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water as will melt it, and put your pulp into the boiling Sugar, ſtirring it continually vntill it be thicke, then pot it and keepe it for vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Conſerue of Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlips, good againſt Melancholy.</head>
               <p n="36">36 GAther them in the heat of the day, &amp; clip only the yellow flower, then take twiſe their weight in fine Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and beate the flowers with one halfe of it, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb facs="tcp:1578:36"/>till the pulp be very fine, and boile the other part to a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Chriſti</hi> height, and put the beaten flowers into the boiling Sugar, and let it boile with continuall ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, vntill it grow ſomething thick, coole it vntill it be but warme, and pot it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p n="37">37 TO make Conſerue of Marigoldes being the ſame vertue, with the laſt Conſerue, is to worke with Marigolds altogether, as with the Cowſlip, without any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:36"/>
               <head>To make Conſerue of Damſons.</head>
               <p n="38">38 TAke a pottle of Damſons, prick them, &amp; put them into a pint of Roſe-water, and as much Claret-wine, couer them, and let them boile in an other veſſell of hot water two houres or more, then incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them well together with a great ſpoone, and when they be tender, coole them and ſtraine them, and ſet the pulp ouer the fire, and put thereto a ſufficient quantity of Sugar, gueſſing it by your taſte, &amp; let the pulp boile vntill it looke of a Damſon colour.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:37"/>
            <head>Tart-ſtuffes.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make an excellent Tart-ſtuffe of Damſons, to laſt all the yeere.</head>
               <p n="39">39 TAke a pottle of Damſons and good ripe Apples pared and cut into quarters, put them into an earthen pot, couer your pot with a piece of courſe Paſte, and bake it in an Ouen with Manchet, and ſtraine it through a ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſeaſon it with Cinamon, Ginger, Sugar, and Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and boile it thick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:37"/>
               <head>To make an excellent Tart-ſtuffe of Prunes.</head>
               <p n="40">40 PVt ſixe faire Pippins pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and cored vnto two or three pound of Prunes, &amp; a pinte of Claret-wine, ſtew them tender, and ſtrain them, ſeaſon them with Cinamon, Ginger, and Sugar, and a little Roſe-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make white Tart-ſtuffe.</head>
               <p n="41">41 TAke a quart of ſweete Creame, the white of ten Egs, ſtraine them, &amp; boile the ſtuffe with quartered Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, a piece of whole Mace, a graine of Muske, then boile
<pb facs="tcp:1578:38"/>it with continuall ſtirring, when it growes thicke like Curds, hang it on a naile in a cloath, to dreine out the Whay, then take out the wholeſpice, and ſtraine it, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it with Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make yellow Tart-ſtuffe.</head>
               <p n="42">42 DRiue the yolks of tenne Egges through a ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with a quart of ſweet Creame, ſeaſon it with Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Ginger, and Sugar, and a little Roſe-water, and let it boile, with continuall ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, vntil it be thick enough.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:38"/>
            <head>Gellies.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Quiddoniock.</head>
               <p n="43">43 TAke out the kernels from eight Peare quinces, the faireſt and yelloweſt that you can get, boile them in a quart of ſpring water vnto a pinte, put in a quarter of a pinte of Damaske Roſe-water, and one pound of fine Sugar, and ſo let it boile vntill it come to a deepe colour, then drop a drop on the bottome of a ſawcer, and if it ſtand; take it off the fire, and let it runne through a gelly-bagge into a
<pb facs="tcp:1578:39"/>Baſon, ouer a chafingdiſh of coales to keepe it warme, and fill your boxes with a ſpoon, but couer them not till they be colde. If you would haue it printed, then you muſt haue moulds of the very ſame big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with your boxes, wet your mould with Roſe-water, and let it runne into them, and when it is colde turne it into your boxes, or elſe if they ſhould be dry, your Gellie would not come out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Chryſtall Gellie.</head>
               <p n="44">44 TAke a knuckle of Veale, and two paire of Calues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feet, flay the feet, and take out
<pb facs="tcp:1578:39"/>the fat betweene the clawes, waſh them in two or three warme waters, &amp; lay them all night in faire water in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pan or pot, the next day boile them tender in cleare ſpring-water from a gallon to three pintes, &amp; let that liquor ſtand in an earthen Baſon, then pare off the top and bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, &amp; put to it ſome Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, ſeaſon it with double refined Sugar, and put to it halfe a dozen ſpoonefuls of oyle of Ciuamon, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Ginger, and likewiſe of Nutmeg and Mace, one grain of Musk in a piece of lawne ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a thrid, put all this being boiled into a ſiluer or earthen
<pb facs="tcp:1578:40"/>diſh, and when it is colde ſlice it and ſerue it in on glaſſe Plates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To preſerue Lemonds to lie in quaking Gellie.</head>
               <p n="45">45 Firſt, purge away their bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, by boiling, and ſhifting them ſeauen or eight times in the boiling, then boile a pinte of Apple-water, and a pound of Sugar, and ſcum it, &amp; take it off when you ſcum it, then put in your Lemond rindes into the hot liquor, and boile them leaſurely in that hot ſirupe, vntill they be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and being almoſt colde, pot it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:40"/>
               <head>To make Gellie of Pippins of Amber colour.</head>
               <p n="46">46 PAre and core eight Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, boile them in a quart of ſpring water, from a quart to a pinte, put in a quarter of a pint of Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, one pound of Sugar, and boile it vncouered vntill it come to a deeper colour, drop a drop on a piece of glaſſe, &amp; if it ſtand, then it is enough, then let it run through a gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bag into a veſſell on a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingdiſh of coales, and while it is warme fill your moulds or boxes with a ſpoone, and let it ſtand till it be colde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:41"/>
               <head>To make Gellie of Pippins as orient as a Rubie.</head>
               <p n="47">47 PAre and core eight Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, boile them in a quart of ſpring water to a pinte, put to it a quarter of a pinte of Roſe-water, a pound of fine Sugar, boile it ſtill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, vntill it be both red and readie: in all other things doe as in the Amber-colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gellie, remembring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies that your moulds be laid in water two or three houres before you vſe them, and drop or knock out the water, but wipe them not, if the Gellie will not eaſily
<pb facs="tcp:1578:41"/>come, but warme the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome neuer ſo little, and it will come out as you wiſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Leach of diuers colours.</head>
               <p n="48">48 LAy halfe a pound of <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane</hi> Almonds in colde water, the next day blanch and beate them in a ſtone morter, put in ſome good Damaske Roſe-water into the beating of them, when they be very fine draw them through a ſtrainer with a quart of ſweete milke from the Cowe, and ſet it on a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing diſh of coales, with a piece
<pb facs="tcp:1578:42"/>of Iſinglaſſe, a piece of whole Mace and Nutmeg quartered, a graine of Muske tyed in a piece of lawne, when it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth thick, take it off the fire, and take out your whole ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and let it runne through a ſtrainer into a broad and deepe diſh, and when it is colde, you may ſo ſlice it and ſerue it in. If you will colour any of it, Saffron is for yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, greene Wheat for green, Turnſoll is for red, and blew bottles in corne giue their owne colour.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:42"/>
            <head>Breads.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make red Ginger-bread, commonly called Leach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbar.</head>
               <p n="49">49 GRate and dry two ſtale Manchets, either by the fire, or in an Ouen, ſift them through a Sieue, and put to it Cinamon, Ginger, Sugar, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorice, Anis-ſeed: when you haue mingled all this toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, boile a pint of red wine, &amp; put in your mingled bread, and ſtirre it, that it be as thick as a Haſtie-pudding; then take it out, and coole it, and
<pb facs="tcp:1578:43"/>mould it with Cinamon, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Liquorice, and Aniſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeede, and rowle it thinne, and print it with your mould, and dry it in a warme Ouen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make white Ginger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread.</head>
               <p n="50">50 TAke halfe a pound of March-pane-Paſt made with Almonds, Roſe-water and Sugar, and a ſpoonefull of <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> ſeaſon it very hot with Ginger mould it vp ſtiffe, rowle it thin, and print it with your moulds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:43"/>
               <head>To make <hi>Italian</hi> Bisket.</head>
               <p n="51">51 BEat and cearſe a pound of double refined Sugar with 2. grains of Musk, foure of Amber-greece, then ſteepe gum-dragon in Roſe-water, and the white of a new laid Egge, beat it in a ſtone mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a perfect Paſte, then rub, drie, and duſt an ounce of Aniſe-ſeede, and worke it into the Paſte on a ſheete of paper like to little Manchets, or print it with moulds, and lay it vpon Marchpane Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and bake it in a warme Ouen, it will be light and white.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:44"/>
               <head>To make an excellent Bread called <hi>Ginetoes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="52">52 TAke halfe a pound of fine Wheat flower, an ounce of powder of Pomecit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, an ounce of powder of Lemonds, a quarter of an ounce of fine cerſed Ginger, the weight of ſixe pence of the fineſt Baſill, Marioram beaten into powder, make all this into a perfect Paſte as ſtiffe as for Manchet, with a little Ipocras made warme, the yolks of three or foure new laid Egges, a ſawcer full of ſweet Creame, a piece of ſweet Butter as much as an
<pb facs="tcp:1578:44"/>Egge, and then rowle it in long rowles, and tie them in ſome pretie faſhion like Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, then throw them into ſeething water, and they will preſently fall downe to the bottome, watch them, and ſo ſoone as you ſee them riſe to the top of the water, take them vp preſently with a ſcummer, and bake them vpon ſheetes of white paper, and when they be three or foure dayes old, throw them into boiling Sugar of a Candie height; then take them vp, and drie them vpon leaues made of Basket-makers twigges in a warme Ouen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:45"/>
               <head>To make Prince Bisket.</head>
               <p n="53">53 DRie a pound of very fine wheat flower in an Ouen two houres, after the bread hath beene drawne, or the Ouen being warmed, but not heated for the nonce, the flower were beſt in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Pipkin couered, leaſt it looſe the colour, put to it a pound of double refined Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar beaten and cearſed fine, then take ten new laid Egges, take away fiue of their whites, ſtraine theſe Egs into a Baſon, with a ſpoonfull of Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſixe ſpoonfuls of ſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Creame, when you haue
<pb facs="tcp:1578:45"/>all in the Baſon, firſt put in your cearſed Sugar, and let it diſſolue by beating it into your Egs, then put in your flower by little and little, vntill both the flower and the other things be incorporated, beat it well together an houre at leaſt, and you ſhall at laſt ſee it turne white, then you muſt haue coffins of white plate indude with butter as thinne as you can, ſo as it be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in euery place, then take an ounce and a halfe of ſweet Aniſe-ſeed, and one of Corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, dried rubd and duſted, put the Aniſe-ſeed in the batter, &amp; the batter into the coffins, and bake it an houre at leaſt if you
<pb facs="tcp:1578:46"/>will, you may make Crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of the ſame batter, driue it thinne vpon the Plates, and when you take it off, rowle it thinne like a Wafer, and dry them againe in the Ouen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make French Maca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roones.</head>
               <p n="54">54 VVAſh a pound of the neweſt and the beſt <hi>Iordane</hi> Almonds in three or foure waters, to take away the redneſſe from their out-ſide, lay them in a Baſon of warme water all night, the next day blanch them, and dry them with a faire cloath, beat them in a ſtone morter, vntillthey
<pb facs="tcp:1578:46"/>be reaſonably fine, put to them halfe a pound of fine beaten Sugar, and ſo beat it to a perfect Paſte, then put in halfe a dozen ſpoonefuls of good Damaske Roſe-water, three graines of Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece, when you haue beaten all this together, dry it on a chafingdiſh of coales vntill it grow white and ſtiffe, then take it off the fire, and put the whites of two new laid Egs firſt beaten into froath, and ſo ſtirre it well together, then lay them on wafers in faſhion of little long rowles, and ſo bake them in an Ouen as hot as for Manchet, but you muſt firſt let the heat of the Ouen
<pb facs="tcp:1578:47"/>paſſe ouer before you put them in, when they riſe white and light, take them out of the Ouen, and put them in a warme platter, and ſet them againe into the warme Ouen, &amp; ſo let them remain foure or fiue houres, and then they wil be throughly dry, but if you like them better being moiſt, then dry them not after the firſt baking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make <hi>Naples</hi> Bisket.</head>
               <p n="55">55 BEat and cearſe a pound of double refined Sugar, a quarter of a pound of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, beat them as fine as you would doe for Almond
<pb facs="tcp:1578:47"/>milke, ſtraine your Almonds with a ſawcer full of ſweete creame, and two or three ſpoonefulls of the beſt Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, then take your afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid powder of Sugar, two or three graines of Muske, foure of Amber-greece, put in three or foure ſpoonefulls of baked flower, and ſo beate it in a ſiluer baſon into batter with a ſiluer ſpoone, and put it into little long coffines, and ſet them againe a drying in a diſh, vntill they be readie, box them and keepe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:48"/>
               <head>To make ſhell bread.</head>
               <p n="56">56 BEate a quarter of a pound of double refined Sugar, cearſe it with two or three ſpoonefulls of the fineſt, the youlkes of three new laid egs, and the white of one, beate all this together in with two or three ſpoonefulls of ſweete creame, a graine of muske, a thimble full of the powder of a dried Lemond, and a little Anniſe-ſeede beaten and cear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and a little Roſe-water, then baſte Muskle-ſhells with ſweete butter, as thinne as you can lay it on with a feather, fill your ſhells with the batter
<pb facs="tcp:1578:48"/>and lay them on a gridiron or a lattiſe of wickers into the ouen, and bake them, and take them out of the ſhells, and iſe them with Roſe-water &amp; Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. It is a delicate bread, ſome call it the Italian Muſhle, if you keepe them any long time, then alwaies in wet wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put them in your ouen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Counteſſe cakes.</head>
               <p n="57">57 TAke halfe a pound of March-pane paſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakte, and put it into a ſtone morter with the youlkes of foure new laid egges, two or three ſpoonefuils of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, as much ſweet creame,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:49"/>ſeaſon it with Cloues, Mace, and Nutmegs, beate your egs, ſpices, and nutmegs well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then ſtraine it with a thimble-full of Coriander; the ſpices being ſo mingled doe ſeaſon, and yet are not ſeene, then grate a Manchet &amp; beat all together in an Alabaſter morter, and powre it on two little round plates, drie them for all the yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make a fine Sugar cake.</head>
               <p n="58">58 BAke a pound of finewheat flower in a pipkin cloſe couered, put thereto halfe a pound of fine Sugar, foure yolkes and one white of egs.
<pb facs="tcp:1578:49"/>Pepper and Nutmegs, ſtraine them with clouted creame, and with a little new Ale yeaſt, make it in paſt, as it were for Manchet, bake it in a quicke ouen with a breath fire in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens mouth, but beware of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:50"/>
            <head>Rough Rock Candies.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Rock <hi>de Cittron.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="59">59 ROwle into little bals halfe a pound of rawe March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane Paſte, flat them like Figges, then take prefer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Pomecittrons, bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, greene Ginger, cut each of theſe fruits an inch long, and prick them into the Marchpane ſtuffe, and ſet them in an Ouen, dry them, and iſe them like a March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane, caſt on Carrawaies, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:50"/>
               <head>To rough-Candie Orenges with Sugar.</head>
               <p n="60">60 TAke a deepe earthen Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and fiue round wires, according to the bigneſſe of the Pan, lay your Orenge rindes on the loweſt wire, and lay another wire on it, and then lade that wire alſo with your fruit, and lay on the third wire, and lade it alſo, and ſo with the reſt, then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all with Sugar boiled to a Candie height, and ſet the Pan vpon a ſoft mat or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion ſeauen or eight houres, then poure out all the Sugar that will run from the wires.
<pb facs="tcp:1578:51"/>and let them drop an houre after, vntill it haue quite done, then take them out, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To rough-Candie ſprigs of Roſemarie.</head>
               <p n="61">61 LAy your Roſemarie bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches one by one vpon a faire ſheete of paper, then take Sugar-candie beaten ſmal like ſparks of diamonds, and wet it in a little Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a ſiluer ſpoone, and lay it as euen as you can vpon euery branch, and ſet them a drying a good way off from the fire, and in one houre they will be dry, then turne them, and candie the other ſide, and
<pb facs="tcp:1578:51"/>when both ſides be throughly dry, box them &amp; keepe them all the yeere they wil appeare to the eye in their natural co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and ſeeme to be couered with ſparks of diamonds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To rough-Candie all manner of flowers in their owne colours, taſtes, and ſmels.</head>
               <p n="62">62 GAther what flowers you will in the heat of the day, when the Sun hath drawn away all the moiſture from them, &amp; vſe them altogether as the Roſemarie. The like practiſe may be with whole Mace, Nutmegs, ſticks of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, or any other dry fruit.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:52"/>
            <head>Sucket-Candies.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To Sucket-Candie greene Lemonds.</head>
               <p n="63">63 VVAſh this fruit with ſeething water, dry it, &amp; put it in a warme Ouen, the next day throw them in hot double refined Sugar, boiled to a Candie height, boile them a walme or two, take them vp and dry them in an Ouen, the next day boxe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:52"/>
               <head>To ſucket-Candie greene Ginger.</head>
               <p n="64">64 VVAſh it, as was ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, dry it in the Ouen, the next day couer it in clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Sugar, boiled to a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die height, &amp;c. but remember that both muſt be firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To ſucket-Candie greene Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, before they be ſheld.</head>
               <p n="65">65 FIrſt, preſerue them as hath beene ſhewed before in the twentie foure Receipt, and
<pb facs="tcp:1578:53"/>then, as the Lemonds and the Ginger, they muſt be waſht from their ſirupe, and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as they.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Peaches, or any other.</head>
               <p n="66">66 GReene Plums may be ſucket-Candied after the very ſame manner, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that they be firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:53"/>
            <head>Cordiall VVaters.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make <hi>Aqua-Coeleſtis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="67">67 TAke ſixe ounces of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, of Cloues one drachme, of Nutmegs one drachme &amp; a halfe, of Cubebs two drachmes, of Calamus rootes one drachme, bruiſe them all, and keepe them in a faire paper: then take Betonie and Sage flowers, of each a handfull, Marioram and Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niroyall of each a handfull, bruiſe them alſo: then take of theſe powders, <hi>Aromaticum Roſarum</hi> three drachmes, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambre Diamargariton frigidum,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:54"/>Diamoſcum dulce,</hi> of each a drachme and ½, put all theſe into a gallon of ſpirit of wine, and ſteepe them three dayes and three nights very cloſe coucred, and ſhake them well together euery morning and euening, then diſtill them in your Limbecke, and hang an ounce of Saunders in the water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Cinamon Water.</head>
               <p n="68">68 TAke one pound of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, the beſt you can get, bruiſe it well, and put to it a gallon of the beſt Sack, and ſteepe it three daies and three nights, and diſtill it as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:54"/>
               <head>To make Doctor <hi>Steuens</hi> Water.</head>
               <p n="69">69 TAke one drachme of Roſe-leaues, Borage, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloſſe, Violets, &amp; Roſemarie flowers, of each a drachme and a halfe, of Spicknard a drachme, of Cinamon two ounces, of Ginger an ounce, Cloues and Nutmegs of each halfe an ounce, of Card a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous a drachme and a halfe, Galingall two drachmes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebs a drachme, Pepper three drachmes, Anniſe-ſeede, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raway-ſeedes and Fennell, of each an ounce, <hi>Lignum</hi> halfe a drachme, Corall and Pearle
<pb facs="tcp:1578:55"/>in fine powder, of each a drachme, bruiſe theſe and put them in a pottle of <hi>Aqua-vitae</hi> and a quart of excellent good Sack, vſing the ſame as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſhewed in <hi>Aqua-Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Balme-water.</head>
               <p n="70">70 TAke fiue ounces of dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Balme, Time, Pennie-Royall, of each three ounces, of Cinamon foure ounces, of Cardamon one drachme, graines halfe an ounce, ſweet Fennell ſeedes an ounce, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs and Ginger of each a drachme, Galingall, <hi>Calamus,</hi> and Cypreſſe, Cubebs, and
<pb facs="tcp:1578:55"/>Pepper of each two drachmes, of <hi>Calamus</hi> rootes halfe a drachme, of <hi>Diptimus</hi> one drachme, bruiſe theſe things, and put them into a pottle of Sack, and ſteepe them twenty foure houres, and vſe them like the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Angelica-water.</head>
               <p n="71">71 TAke a handfull of dried <hi>Carduus,</hi> of Angelica rootes three ounces, of Myrrh one drachme, Nutmegs halfe an ounce, of Cinamon and Ginger, foure ounces of each, Saffron one drachme and a halfe, <hi>Cardamons,</hi> Cubebs, Galingall and Pepper, of each
<pb facs="tcp:1578:56"/>a quarter of an ounce, Mace two drachmes, Graines one drachme, <hi>Lignum Aloes.</hi> Spick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, <hi>Iunius adoratus,</hi> of each a drachme, Sage, Borage, Bogloſſe, Violets and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie flowers, of each a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them and ſteepe them in a pottle of Sack twelue houres, and then &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Wormewood water.</head>
               <p n="73">73 TAke foure ounces of Wormewood, Sage, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, and Rew, of each a handfull, Roſemarie tops a handfull, Cinamon three ounces, Nutmegs halfe an ounce, Cloues and Mace, of
<pb facs="tcp:1578:56"/>each halfe a drachme, Ginger an ounce Galingall, Cubebs, and Spicknard, of each a drachme and ½, of <hi>Scordium</hi> halfe a handfull, bruiſe theſe and put them in a pottle of Sack, and a pint of <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> ſteepe them 24. houres. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:57"/>
            <head>Conceits in Sugar-Workes.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make March-pane Paſte.</head>
               <p n="73">73 CEarſe the fineſt and the whiteſt refined Sugar, to euery third ſpoonfull thereof take a blauncht <hi>Iordane</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, ſtampe them in a ſmooth morter, and now and then put in two or three drops of Roſe-water. It muſt be extreamely much beaten before it wil be a perfect paſt, at the leaſt an houre.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:57"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make a March-pane, to iſe, and garniſh it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Art.</head>
               <p n="74">74 BLaunch and beate two pound of <hi>Iordane</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds in a ſtone morter, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in now &amp; then a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Roſe-water, to keepe them from oyling: when they are beaten fine, put to them a pound and a halfe of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt cearſed Sugar, and now and then a ſpoonfull more of Roſe-water, as your ſelfe ſhall ſee requiſite, incorporate them, which with much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour muſt be effected: when
<pb facs="tcp:1578:58"/>you haue brought them to a perfect paſte, then rowle it to what breadth you will, but it muſt be thin, make a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome to it with Wafers, ſet an edge to it round about, and pinch it then bake it, and ice it with Roſe-water and Sugar beaten like batter, and ſpread it on with a fea her, and ſo put it againe into the Ouen, or baking-pan, when you ſee it riſe white, and ſhining like ice, take it out againe, and ſticke in your ſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, as namely golden Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigolds, and long Comfits, or ſuch like, caſt on Biskets and Carrawaies, and lay Bay leaues vnder it, appearing
<pb facs="tcp:1578:58"/>with the leaues end without the Marchpane round about.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make any Conceit in March-pane-ſtuffe.</head>
               <p n="75">75 MOuld ſome of your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ſtuffe with cearſed Sugar, &amp; make ſome vp like little ſquare pies, fill them with drie ſuckets, cut in ſmall peeces, or drye Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulade; caſt on them colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Biskets and Carrawaies, gild them &amp; ſerue them to the board, you may make ſome of it like collops &amp; bacon, to doe which you muſt haue both red and white paſt, and rowle them both and cut it ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart
<pb facs="tcp:1578:59"/>and lay one on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like bacon, the red muſt be colonied with Roſa Paris and Saunders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make any other conceit as Buttons, Beades, Chaines, &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="76">76 HAuing faſhioned your buttons made of this ſtuffe all of a bigneſſe, either with your hand and knife, or in a mould, if with a knife, then you may turne vp the ridges and the nib, like the threds of ſilke buttons, and the ground-worke is white of it ſelfe, if you will haue them greene and white, then temper
<pb facs="tcp:1578:59"/>ſap-green with gum-Arabick water on the top of your pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill, and ſtrike it downe the ridges of the button, not tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the button on the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. If you will haue them ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, then ſtrike them downe with ſhell-ſiluer, the like may be done with ſhell-gold. If blew, then Azur being firſt ſteept in vinegar; for elſe it is verie dangerous, the vinegar killeth the ſtrength of the blew: If you would haue them red, then vſe <hi>Roſa-paris</hi> on the top of your penſil: when theſe buttons be readie and drie, you may ſet them vpon a card of Sugar plate, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten them with Gum-dragon
<pb facs="tcp:1578:60"/>ſteept in damaske Roſe-water and the owne paſte tempred verie ſoft; ſerue it in on plates of glaſſe, or keepe it as long as you will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Snakes, Snailes, Frogs, Roſes, Cheries, &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="77">77 TAke ſingle mouldes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued inward, according to the forme of the things na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or any other, what you will, then take double refined Sugar, and as much water, or rather Roſe-water as will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue it, and boyle it to a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die height: then take your mouldes, hauing ſteept them two or three houres before in
<pb facs="tcp:1578:60"/>colde water, and fill them with the hot Sugar, and when it is colde turne it out of your moulde, and drie it with a faire cloath, and it will haue the true forme graued or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the mould. But for your Cherries, ſtrawberries, and ſuch like, take double mouldes, wet them in water, and fill them with hot Sugar, then take a ſmall birchen twig, dried before in a feather-makers or diers fat, and prick them in the noſe of the mould into the hot Sugar, and when they be colde, take them out and drie them, and they will be as though they grew vpon ſtaulkes; then colour them as
<pb facs="tcp:1578:61"/>is ſhewed in the order of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours in the end of this booke, but if you will make Roſes you muſt make them of Sugar plate paſt (mentioned in the foureſcore and one receipt) rowled verie thin, &amp; then you muſt cut the leaues ſingle with an inſtrument of tynne made for the ſame purpoſe, &amp; then faſten one leafe vpon another, as in the laſt receipt was ſhewed, and ſtick them on the top of a birchen-twig, pilde and dipt in the fat, and they will be white Roſes, but you may colour them as is elſe-where ſhewed. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, you may make Burrage, Cowſlips, Primroſes, ſtock-Gilliflowers,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:61"/>Marigoldes, &amp;c. keepe them drie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Shooes, Slippers, Keyes, Kniues, Gloues, &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="78">78 ALL theſe and ſuch like things, you may make of Sugar plate paſte, cut them with your knife, but faſhion &amp; finiſh them only with your hand and pincers, but if you want handines, or haue no leiſure, then you muſt haue mouldes of tynne, and hauing fitted your paſte, cut it with the mouldes, drie them ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:62"/>
               <head>To make Letters, Knots, or any other Iumball for a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet quicklie.</head>
               <p n="79">79 YOu muſt take ſingle mouldes carued inward, either in wood or ſtone, with the true forme of what you would haue, lay them in cold water: then take double refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sugar, and as much Roſe-water as will diſſolue it, boile it to a Candie height, then take the mouldes out of the water, ſhake out the water, but wipe them not, and fill your Letters or Knots with the hot Sugar, and when they be colde and hard, turne them
<pb facs="tcp:1578:62"/>out, and wipe them with a faire cloath.</p>
               <p>There is alſo another way to make theſe or ſuch things, thus: Take drie ſingle moulds, duſt them through a Lawne or Tiffanie Sieue, then take Sugar-plate paſte, or Almond paſte, wrought vnto a good temper, and fill your mould, then cut it off ſmooth and euen, with the top of your mouldes, and turne it out, the reſt of your ſtuffe you may make in long Iumballs about the bigneſſe of a Gooſe quill, and then you may knit it in double knots, or turne it in forme of capital letters, or like claſpes &amp; eyes, or wax-lights</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:63"/>
               <head>To make a Walnut, both ſhell, and Kernill.</head>
               <p n="80">80 MAke a paſte of fine cear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Cinamon and Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, mingled with twiſe ſo much Sugar, cearſed alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine, &amp; a little Muske, print it in a double moulde, made in like vnto a Wallnut with ſhells, then cloſe them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with gumme dragon ſteept in Roſe-water, and if you will haue a Kernill in it, then you muſt haue another double mould for the Kernill, but you muſt make the Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nill of white Sugar plate, and
<pb facs="tcp:1578:63"/>when it is throughly drie, you muſt ouer-lay it with a little ſaffron that it may be like the skinne of the Kernill.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Sugar workes of another ſort.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Sugar plate paſte.</head>
               <p n="81">81 TAke a pound of double refined Sugar, put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three ounces of the beſt ſtarch, if you drie the Sugar after it is in pouder, it will the ſooner paſſe through the Lawne ſieue: then cearſe it
<pb facs="tcp:1578:64"/>on a faire ſheete of paper, and ſweepe it on a heape with a feather or a wing, and in the middeſt of the heape, you muſt put a lumpe of gumme-draggon, about the bigneſſe of a wallnut, firſt ſteeped in Roſe-water (a little porrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger full of Roſe-water, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to diſſolue an ounce of gumme, which gumme muſt be very cleane pict from all droſſe &amp; ſtrained through a canuis ſtrainer,) temper this gumme with the white of an egge, and with the Sugar, a little at once, vntill you haue wrought vp all the gumme &amp; the Sugar into a ſtiffe paſte: you muſt alwaies in the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:1578:64"/>haue ſome of the gumme, and ſome of the Sugar, and before you moulde it in the moulde, you muſt firſt duſt your moulde with cearſed Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make paſte of diuers ſorts of flowers as Violets, Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlips, Marigolds, Roſes, Gilliflowers, &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="82">82 MAke a pouder of theſe flowers, being drie, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king onely their ſweete leafe, and put thereto fine pouder of Cinamon and a little Muske, if you haue it, mingled well together then boile the waight of the pouder in fine
<pb facs="tcp:1578:65"/>Sugar, with as much Roſe-water as will diſſolue it. If your worke be with Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golds, put to it a little Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, boile it, and to your worke adde the pap of a Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin dried on a chafingdiſh with coales in a ſiluer or ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then diſh, and ſprinkled with Roſe-water, and wrought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Paſte, then bray ſome Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-candie, but not to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, wet Gum-dragon, and with the ſame make it ſticke in your paſte, and ſo it will ſeeme to be rock candied, cut the paſte with a knife ſteept in Roſe-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:65"/>
               <head>To make an excellent Pennet, good againſt colde.</head>
               <p n="83">83 BEat foure ounces of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-candy vnto fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, put to it a thimble-full of Engliſh Liquorice, beaten and cearſed, three drops of Chimicall oyle of Aniſe-ſeed, a graine of Muske, beat all this to paſte, with Gum-dragon ſteept in Damask Roſe-water, and when you haue beaten it to perfect paſte, rowle it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſheet of white paper into rowles, about the bigneſſe of a wheat ſtraw, and cut it in pieces about an inch long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:66"/>
               <head>To make Cinamon ſtickes by Art.</head>
               <p n="84">84 TAke a quarter of a pound of fine cearſed Cinamon, and halfe an ounce of fine cearſed Ginger, mingle it with halfe a pound of fine cearſed Sugar two graines of Muske; beat all together into a perfect paſte, with Gum-dragon ſteept in Roſe water, in an Alabaſter or ſtone mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, rowle it thin on a ſheete of paper, duſted through a cearſe with beaten Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and then wrap it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Reedes, and when it is almoſt dry, draw it eaſily
<pb facs="tcp:1578:66"/>off the Reedes, and dry them throughly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Calliſhones.</head>
               <p n="85">85 TAke halfe a pound of Marchpane paſte, a thim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-full of Coriander ſeedes beaten to powder, with a graine of Muske, beat all to a perfect paſte, print it, and drie it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Muſcachones.</head>
               <p n="86">86 TAke batter made as for Prince Bisket, in the 53. Receipt, put to it two ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Cheeſe-curds, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Ginger, Sugar, and a
<pb facs="tcp:1578:67"/>graine of Muske, beat all into the batter, and take a batter ſpout, and ſpout it in long rowles on a ſheete of paper, duſted through a Sieue with fine Sugar, and before they be dry, tye them in ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie knots, and ſo dry them, and then guild them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Muſcadinaes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called kiſſing-Comfits.</head>
               <p n="87">87 TAke halfe a pound of double refined Sugar, beaten and cearſed, with two graines of Musk, three grains of Amber-greece, and a drachme of Orice powder,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:67"/>beat all to a perfect paſte in an Alabaſter morter, then ſleeke a ſheete of white paper with a Sleek-ſtone, and rowle your Sugar paſte, then cut it in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Lozenges with a rowle, and dry them in a Stoue, they will ſerue to garniſh a March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane or other diſhes. If you will haue any red, you muſt mingle it with <hi>Roſa Paris,</hi> if blew, then with blew bottles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Troces, againſt the colde.</head>
               <p n="88">88 BEat two ounces of Sugar-candie to fine powder, put to it a little iuyce of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorice, iuice of Horehound,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:68"/>of Mayden-haire, beate all into a perfect paſte, and rowle it as ſmall as Wheat ſtrawes, cut them an inch and ½. long, dry them, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Cinamon Letters.</head>
               <p n="89">89 TAke paſte made as for <hi>Gemilliſſoes,</hi> colour it with Cinamon, and rowle it in long rowles, as neere as you can all of a bigneſſe, and thereof make faire capitall Romane letters, according to ſome exact patterne, cut in thinne board or white plate, gild them and make a croſſe in the beginning of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:68"/>
               <head>To make <hi>Canalones</hi> in Spices.</head>
               <p n="90">90 TAke halfe a pound of ſif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sugar, put thereto a graine of Muske, Cinamon and Ginger, a little powder of a dried Lemond, beat all this to a perfect paſte with Gum-dragon ſteept in Roſe-water, rowle it thin, and print it with a ſhallow mould, then rowle it vpon Reedes very thin, dry them leaſurely, and keepe them dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:69"/>
               <head>To make Ruſhilians.</head>
               <p n="91">91 TAke a pinte of bakt flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, an ounce of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a quarter of an ounce of beaten Ginger, a graine of Muske, mingle theſe with a pound of beaten Sugar, then take ſixe yolks and ſweet but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, two or three ſpoonefuls of ſweet Creame, make all this into a perfect paſte, and it will looke of Cinamon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, then coole it in ſmall rowles, and make it in letters or knots, dry them in a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Pan.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:69"/>
               <head>To make Gentilliſſoes.</head>
               <p n="92">92 BAke and cearſe a pound of double refined Sugar, beat it to a perfect paſte, w th the whites of two Egges, and Gum-dragon ſteept in Roſe-water, one graine of Muske, and as much Amber-greece, rowle it in fine rowles and bake it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Nouelliſſoes.</head>
               <p n="93">93 TAke the paſte of your Gentilliſſoes, rowle it thin &amp; fine with red Almond paſt, pinch it with your nippers, &amp; bake it as in the Gentilliſſoes,
<pb facs="tcp:1578:70"/>alwaies prouided that you put Muske and Amber-greece in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make Lozenges of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolets.</head>
               <p n="94">94 TAke Violets, Cowſlips, Roſemarie flowers, or any other in the heat of the day, ſhred onely the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt of the bloſſomes vpon a trencher, with a ſharp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knife, in as many pieces, and as fine as poſſibly you can, and then beat them as fine as may be in an Alabaſter mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with the pap of a Pippin, and a graine of Muske, then boile double refined Sugar to a Candy height, and put your
<pb facs="tcp:1578:70"/>beaten flowers into the boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sugar, and boile it a little longer, for the flowers will bring the Sugar back againe, and when you ſee it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thicke, powre it on a ſheet of glaſſe, and cut it into little Lozenges like Wigs, ſome you may drop.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:71"/>
            <head>To dry Fruits.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To dry Orenges and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</head>
               <p n="95">95 RAſpe the skinnes of theſe fruits, cut them in halfes, and take out the cores, lay the rindes preſently in faire water two or three dayes, to take away their bitterneſſe, then boile them fiue or ſixe times, in ſeueral waters for the ſame purpoſe, and when they be tender take them vp, and dry them in a faire cloath; then couer them in clarified Sugar, and boile it leaſurely
<pb facs="tcp:1578:71"/>two houres, then take them off, and put them in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Pipkin, and let them ſo remaine foure or fiue dayes, or longer the better, when you will dry them, ſet them on the fire againe vntill they be through hot, drain them, and the whileſt boile freſh Sugar to a Candie height, then put them in, take them out, and lay them on a basket-makers lattice, and dry them in a warme Ouen in one night, and they are ready.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To dry white Peare-Plums.</head>
               <p n="96">96 GAther the faireſt of this fruit before they bee
<pb facs="tcp:1578:72"/>throughly ripe, pricke them with a Pen-knife, and couer them in clarified Sugar, heat them on the fire vntill they crack, then take them vp, and put freſh Sugar to that ſirupe, and boile it a good deale higher, now and then taking it off and ſcumming it cleane: then put in the Plums againe, and warme them againe in the hot Sugar about halfe an houre, then poure them into a pot or glaſſe, and let them remaine 3. or 4. dayes in that hot Sugar, then warme againe theſe Plums, and ſet them a cooling; then boile as much freſh Sugar as will couer them vnto a candie height, and put
<pb facs="tcp:1578:72"/>the plums into that hot Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and ſo let it boile leyſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a quarter of an houre, now and then turning them, for that will make them take Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, then take them vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene hot and colde, and lay them on a ſheete of glaſſe, and ſo drie them in a ſtoue, or in a warme Ouen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To drie blacke Pear-eplums.</head>
               <p n="97">97 GAther this fruit alſo in a faire ſun-ſhine day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two or three of the clocke, when the ſunne hath taken off all the outward moiſture from them, which otherwiſe would hinder the worke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:73"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:73"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:74"/>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>In all other practiſe doe as in the white peare-plum hath beene ſhewed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To drie Pippins cleere at Amber.</head>
               <p n="98">98 PAre this fruit, and cut out the coare, and ſo ſoone as you haue prepared a piece, caſt it into a baſon of faire running water, then boile the weight thereof in clarified Sugar vnto a Candie height, then drie your Pippins with a faire cloath, and boile them apace in the hot Sugar, and euer when you ſee any froth, take them off the fire and ſcum them verie cleane, then
<pb facs="tcp:1578:74"/>turne them and ſet them on againe and boile them apace; then (as before) take them off and ſcum them, and ſet them on the fire againe, and doe ſo halfe a dozen times at at the leaſt and when your Sugar is at a Candie height, take out your pippins and put them in a warme Ouen, and let them ſtay two or three houres, and they will be drie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To drie Apricockes orient and verie cleere.</head>
               <p n="99">99 TAke faire large Apri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks well coloured, but not too ripe, pare and ſtone
<pb facs="tcp:1578:75"/>them, and couer them in cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Sugar, boile them ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely turning them, &amp; ſcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them verie often: then take them off the fire, and let them ſtand all night in that ſirupe, the next day warme them againe, and when they be hot, take them out, and ſet them a dreining againe, then boile other Sugar a little higher with the Apricockes leyſurely, now and then turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, &amp; ſcumming them, and let them ſtand in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe vntill the next day; the next day warme them againe, and then lay them a dreining, then boile other Sugar to a Candie height, and put the
<pb facs="tcp:1578:75"/>Apricockes into the boiling Sugar, turne them vntill you ſee the Candie grow about them, &amp; lay them on a ſheete of glaſſe, and ſet them into a warme Ouen after the bread hath beene drawne, and let them ſtand about three houres, the next day take them out and turne them, &amp; doe ſo a weeke at leaſt; for they will be verie long a dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To drie Peares without any Sugar.</head>
               <p n="100">100 PAre your Norwich Pare, or any other of the beſt that you can get, but leaue
<pb facs="tcp:1578:76"/>the ſtaulke and the peepe on, prick it with a penknife, and put them into a earthen pot, and bake them a little in an Ouen, then put them vpon ſtraw or bents, into a white plate or latten-pan into an Ouen preſently after the drawing of the bread, doe ſo a weeke together, or longer, and the fruit will laſt the longer.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:76"/>
            <head>Phyſicall Receipts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Phyſitians of this Realme.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make ſirupe of Violets.</head>
               <p n="101">101 PIck and weigh the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of violets put them in a quart of water, and ſtew them vpon hot embers vntill the flowers haue made the water as blew as themſelues, then boile that infuſion vnto a ſirupe with foure pound of clarified Sugar vpon a gentle
<pb facs="tcp:1578:77"/>fire with ſcumming now and then, if the fire be too hot all is mard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To make ſirupe of Liquorce.</head>
               <p n="102">102 SCrape eight ounces of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorice verie cleane and bruiſe it, take an ounce of Maidenhaire, one ounce of Anniſe-ſeede, and as much Fennill-ſeede, ſteepe theſe in foure pintes of raine water and boile it to a quart, then boile the liquour, with one pound and a halfe of Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:77"/>
               <head>To make ſirupe of Roſes ſolutiue.</head>
               <p n="103">103 PLucke the leaues of da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske Roſes, and put them to a gallon of hot water, and ſet it on embers in a great veſſell of boiling liquor, the more leyſurely it boiles, the better it is, and when the leaues looke white, take them vp, and put in freſh, and doe ſo three or foure times, and when the water is red, to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pinte put the white of an egge, and a pound of clarified Sugar, boile it to a ſirupe: the thicker it is the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:78"/>
               <head>To make ſirupe of drie Roſes.</head>
               <p n="104">104 TAke foure ounces of red Roſes dried, and infuſe them in a quart of faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vpon hot embers, vntill the Roſes haue loſt their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, then take a pound and a halfe of clarified Sugar, clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your liquour &amp; Sugar with two Egs, and boile it to the height of a ſirupe vpon a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſoft fire, for if it be ouer hot, the ſirupe will bee of no vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:78"/>
               <head>Againſt the trembling of the heart.</head>
               <p n="105">105 LEt the Patient drink three or foure ſpoonefuls of Claret wine, halfe ſo much Damaske Roſe-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An excellent medicine againſt the riſing of the mother, taught and tried by diuers.</head>
               <p n="106">106 TAke the bigneſſe of a Peaſe of Methridate, and mingle the ſame with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue of Roſes, as much in quantitie as a Walnut, and let the partie eate ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:1578:79"/>euery morning faſting, and euery euening as much for the ſpace of three dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or as long as neede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An Almond milke made for the cooling of the liuer and bloud, it was taught by a Doctor of very good note, for a great perſonage.</head>
               <p n="107">107 TAke Suckorie rootes, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparagus,</hi> and Marſh-Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, of each the weight of eighteene pence in ſiluer, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell rootes as much, the tops of the flowſing of Borage, Bugloſſe, and Scabious, of each a handfull, boile this in
<pb facs="tcp:1578:79"/>a pinte and a quarter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> water vnto a pinte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> make the milke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A remedie againſt looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Bodie.</head>
               <p n="108">108 TAke a pinte of red wine, and halfe an ounce of beaten Cinamon, boile it on the fire, &amp; thicken it with the yolks of foure raw Egs; brew them well, and drinke euery morning halfe a pinte, and euery euening as much. It is beſt in the full or change of the Moone, but good al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:80"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Receipt to make a vomit.</head>
               <p n="109">109 STampe three or foure leaues of <hi>Aſſara,</hi> Tobacco that growes in the Gardens, and ſtraine it with ſixe ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Ale, and drinke it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, faſting halfe an houre after or longer: then take warme Poſſet-drinke, and keepe your ſelfe walking vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the vomit haue done wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; if it worke not as you wiſh, then take more Poſſet-drinke, and ſtill walke till it hath done working, and keepe a good diet at leaſt that day after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:80"/>
               <head>To ſtay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <p n="110">110 TAke ſirupe of Liq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, of May denhaire, of Horehound, of Iſope, of each a like quantity, Conſerue of a Foxe lungs, of <hi>Ale-cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane</hi> (if the partie be enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Ale-cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane</hi> muſt be left out.)</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1578:81"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ordering of Colours.</head>
            <p n="111">111 SAp-greene, <hi>Roſa-Paris,</hi> blew Biſe, yellow Smalt, all theſe colours muſt bee ground with thinne gum-Arabicke water, and are fit to garniſh, but perillous to eate.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Colours that may be eaten.</head>
               <p n="112">112 A White Roſe dried, and ground with Alome wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, maketh a faire ſtraw co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:81"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the heat of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dried, and power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his owne colour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and a little gum Arabicke water.</p>
               <p>The ſecond barke of an Elder, ground with gum-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and a little Alome, maketh a faire greene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Other Colours to colour Leach.</head>
               <p n="113">113 YOur Saffron water ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a yellow: iuyce of greene Wheat in the blade, maketh a greene: Turnſoll gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a red, and the white is of it ſelfe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:82"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:82"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:84"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1578:84"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
